Guide to the James Joyce collection, [ca. 1893]-1941
Joyce, James collection, [ca. 1893]-1941
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
James Joyce collection, [ca. 1893]-1941 (bulk 1901-1920)
4609
James Joyce, 1882-1941.
5.7 linear ft.
Manuscripts, letters, documents, photographs, bound manuscripts, galley proofs, and broadsides.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Manuscripts, letters, documents, photographs, bound manuscripts, galley proofs, and broadsides by, to or about James Joyce, mainly in the early years of his writing career. Manuscripts include the earliest known manuscript of his first book of poems, Chamber Music; a typescript of the first sketch of Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man; an essay containing an important early statement of Joyce's literary theory; and manuscripts for parts of Dubliners, Stephen Hero, Ulysses, Pomes Penyeach, and his play Exiles.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Twentieth-century Irish novelist.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Manuscripts, letters, documents, photographs, bound manuscripts, galley proofs, and broadsides by, to or about James Joyce, mainly in the early years of his writing career. Manuscripts include the earliest known manuscript of his first book of poems, Chamber Music; a typescript of the first sketch of Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man; an essay containing an important early statement of Joyce's literary theory; and manuscripts for parts of Dubliners, Stephen Hero, Ulysses, Pomes Penyeach, and his play Exiles.
Letters include substantial correspondence within the Joyce family; substantial correspondence between Joyce and his lover Nora Barnacle, later Nora Joyce, including erotic love letters from Joyce to her; and some fifty letters from Ezra Pound. Also included are correspondence and documents relating to the publication of Joyce's work, with his literary agent James B. Pinker, his patron Harriet Shaw Weaver, publishers Elkin Mathews and Grant Richards, and others. Other correspondents include Oliver St. John Gogarty; Monro, Saw & Co., the law firm which administered Harriet Shaw Weaver's patronage of Joyce; John Quinn, and W.B. Yeats.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Joyce, James, 1882-1941.; Gogarty, Oliver St. John, 1878-1957.; Joyce, Charles.; Joyce, James, 1882-1941.; Joyce, John S.; Joyce, May.; Joyce, Nora Barnacle, 1884-1951.; Joyce, Stanislaus, 1884-1955.; Mathews, Elkin, 1851-1921.; Murray, Josephine.; Pinker, James B.; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972.; Quinn, John.; Richards, Grant, 1872-1948.; Weaver, Harriet Shaw.; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939.; Monro, Saw and Co.
Subjects:
English literature--20th century.; Irish literature.; Modernism (Literature).; Authors and publishers.; Domestic relations--Ireland.; Authors, Irish.; Love-letters.; Erotica.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Portraits.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Abreviations: AL Autographed Letter, AM Autographed Manuscript, AD Autographed Document, D Document, DS Document Signed, TM Typed Manuscript.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Organized into these series: Manuscripts by Joyce; letters by him; letters by others to or about Joyce; photographs and unidentified and miscellaneous material.
Manuscripts arranged alphabetically by title; letters by Joyce, in chronological order; letters by others, alphabetically by author.
Series List
Series I. Manuscripts
Boxes 1-2, and bound manuscripts
Series II. Documents and Miscellaneous
Box 3
Series III. Outgoing Correspondence
March 1901-December 1905 - Box 4
July 1906-August 1911 - Box 5
April 1912-January 1941 - Box 6
Series IV. Incoming Correspondence, Manuscripts and Documents
Boxes 7-14
Series V. Photographs and Miscellaneous
Box 15
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Manuscripts
  - Autograph copies of two songs by Ben Jonson, ca. 1903-1904; AM (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1 leaf. Copies on recto and verso of single slip of paper. Song 3 from The Metamorphos'd Gypsies and "Give end unto thy pastimes, Love" Scholes 19.
  - "La Battaglia fra Bernard Shaw e la Censura. Blanco Posnet Smascherato", Sept. 5, 1909; TM (Box 1, Folder 2)
    6 leaves. Written in Trieste. With two copies of English translation. Published in Il Piccolo della Sera Sept. 5, 1909. Typescript dated August 31. Scholes 39.
  - Review of The Bruno Philosophy by J. Lewis McIntyre, Oct. 30, 1903; TM (Box 1, Folder 3)
    4 leaves. Typed transcripts from The Daily Express of October 30, 1903 in two copies. Scholes 1387.
  - Chamber Music Poems II-XXXII, 1902-1904; AM (Box 1, Folder 4)
    36 leaves. In final or nearly final form; some poems bearing pencil emendations by Joyce. Includes four poems not included in the final text. In the hands of James Joyce, Stanislaus Joyce [?], and perhaps another hand. Cf. Scholes 12. Scholes 21.
  - Fragment of Poem XXI of Chamber Music, ca. 1904; AM (Box 1, Folder 5)
    1 leaf. Written in The Tower, Sandycove. On stationary of "The Tower, Sandycove." Scholes 23.
  - Fragment of Christmas Eve, ca. 1904; AM (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1 leaf. Third page of a story by James Joyce. A fair copy on one leaf of wove paper. First line reads "by on Wellington Quay. They used often to meet at Swans." Scholes 29.
  - "La Citta delle Tribu", Aug. 1912; TM (Box 1, Folder 7)
    6 leaves. Written in Galway City. Published in Il Piccolo della Sera Aug. 11, 1912. With typescript English translation. Scholes 39.
  - "La Cometa del 'Home Rule'", Dec. 20, 1910; TM (Box 1, Folder 8)
    4 leaves. Written in Trieste. Published in Il Piccolo della Sera Dec. 20, 1910. With partial English translation. Scholes 39.
  - Fragment of "Dooleysprudence", ca. 1916-1920; AM (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1 leaf. A fragment of a song set to music by James Joyce. Five bars of words and music of a song, in Joyce's hand on paper ruled for musical composition. Scholes 60.
  - "The Dead" from Dubliners, ca. 1906-1910; TM & AM (Box 1, Folder 10)
    56 leaves. Manuscript begins as a typescript and is completed in the hand of an amanuensis. Contains some corrections in James Joyce's hand. Scholes 31.
  - "Ivy Day in the Committee Room" from Dubliners, [n.d.]; AM (Box 1, Folder 11)
    21 leaves. Autograph manuscript with notations for insertions of printed slips--cf. Scholes 33. Not in Scholes
  - Printed slip with passage from "Ivy Day in the Committee Room", ca. Aug. 1911; TM (Box 1, Folder 12)
    1 leaf. Slips like this were printed by Joyce for inclusion in a circular letter to the press written during his dispute with Maunsel over Dubliners. The first sentences read "--But look here, John, --said Mr O'Connor. --Why should we welcome the king of England? Didn't Parnell himself?" Scholes 33.
  - "The Sisters" from Dubliners, ca. Apr. 1905; AM (Box 1, Folder 13)
    15 leaves. This is the text of the Dubliners version of the story, not of the shorter Irish Homestead version. This autograph manuscript was probably used to set up the Maunsel edition of Dubliners, but the final text of "The Sisters" is slightly different from this manuscript. Scholes 30.
  - Transcripts of reviews of Dubliners, Summer 1914; AM (Box 1, Folder 14)
    36 leaves. In various hands, including that of James Joyce. Scholes 51.
  - Transcript of Italian review of Dubliners, 1914; AM (Box 1, Folder 15)
    1 leaf. Scholes 51.
  - [Notebook] "The English Drama", [n.d.]; AM (Box 1, Folder 16)
    6 leaves. Essentially notations, arranged chronologically, ranging from drama's "Religious origins" in the Greek and Hindu traditions to "Elizabethan Drama." For use in a lecture? Not in Scholes.
  - "An Epiphany"- dialogue between Oliver St. John Gogarty and a shop assistant, ca. 1904; AM (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Written in Dublin. 1 leaf. An autograph manuscript on one side of a leaf of good-quality laid paper. A rough draft with corrections and blots. Scholes 18.
  - Fragment of Exiles, [n.d.]; AM (Box 1, Folder 18)
    22 small leaves. Enclosed in an envelope. Not in Scholes.
  - "Il Fenianismo. (L'Ultimo Feniano)", Mar. 22, 1907; TM (Box 1, Folder 19)
    5 leaves. Written in Trieste. One of a series of articles by Joyce published in Il Piccolo della Sera. With partial English translation of Italian text. Scholes 39.
  - Unidentified poem- "The flower I gave", [n.d.]; AM (Box 1, Folder 20)
    1 leaf. Autograph manuscript in pencil on the first page of a ruled piece of wove paper. There are some changes in the first line. A poem of three quatrains. Scholes 50.
  - Draft of "Gas from a Burner", Sept. 15, 1912; AM (Box 1, Folder 21)
    1 leaf. An early draft, probably the first, of this broadside by James Joyce. An autograph manuscript in pencil beginning with the line, "To show you for strictures I don't care a button." The title, "Falconer addresses the Vigilance Committee," appears on the right-hand margin. The text is on the verso of the second leaf of a printed form of an empty royalty agreement from Maunsel and Co., Ltd., on a wove double-leaf. Scholes 46.
  - Draft of "Gas from a Burner", Sept. 15, 1912; AM (Box 1, Folder 22)
    1 leaf. "Written in the train between Flushing and Salzburg." A later draft of this broadside. Autograph manuscript in pencil with ink corrections of the entire 98 line poem. The paper used for this draft was originally a typed copy of an agreement (unsigned) between Joyce and the Maunsel firm. Scholes 47.
  - Draft [final?] of "Gas from a Burner", Sept. 1912; AM (Box 1, Folder 23)
    1 leaf. Written in Flushing. Fair copy of the broadside by James Joyce. An autograph manuscript of the entire poem in ink in an especially legible hand. There are a few changes in ink in the text of the poem. Scholes 48.
  - "Gas from a Burner" [Printed Broadside] [photostat], Sept. 1912; TM (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Written in Trieste. 1 leaf. This broadside was printed in Trieste in an edition of 100 copies. 40 of these were sent to Charles Joyce for distribution in Dublin. This photostat shows a hand-written note added in ink by Joyce dated July 1912.
  - Fragment of "Giacomo Clarenzio Mangan", May 1907; AM (Box 1, Folder 25)
    1 leaf. Autograph manuscript written on one side of a leaf of white wove paper. Corrections are in ink in the left margin. In the upper corner is the number 11 in pencil. This is the page 11 that is missing from Slocum E17a and from the published version in Critical Writings. Scholes 42.
  - Fragments of "Giacomo Clarenzio Mangan", May 1907; TM (Box 1, Folder 26)
    14 leaves. Written in Trieste. A typed transcript of manuscript fragments of a lecture by James Joyce on the Irish poet Mangan, delivered in Italian in Trieste, with carbon copy. Scholes 41.
  - Transcripts of critical material relating to Shakespeare's Hamlet, 1912; AM (Box 1, Folder 27)
    62 pages on 60 leaves. Written in Trieste. Likely for preparation of a series of lectures by Joyce on Hamlet in 1912. This autograph manuscript consists largely of historical and literary excerpts to be used in reference to specific acts and scenes of the play. Some material is marked for use in an introduction and a conclusion. Two pages consist of notes that seem separate from the excerpts. Not in Scholes.
  - Fragment of "The Holy Office", May 23, 1905; AM (Box 1, Folder 28)
    1 leaf. Written in Trieste. Fragment of manuscript with printer's slip attached. This autograph manuscript is the last page of the final draft, numbered "4" in pencil. It is a fair copy made for the Triestine printer on white wove paper. Pasted to the top of the manuscript is the slip of the printer, L. Smolars, with the notation (among others) that 100 copies were to be printed. Scholes 26.
  - "Home Rule Maggiorenne", May 19, 1907; TM (Box 1, Folder 29)
    4 leaves. Written in Trieste. Text, in Italian, of article Joyce published in Il Piccolo della Sera, with English translation. Scholes 39.
  - "L'Irlanda alla Sbarra", Sept. 16, 1907; TM (Box 1, Folder 30)
    4 leaves. Written in Trieste. Text, in Italian, of article published by Joyce in Il Piccolo della Sera, with English translation. Scholes 39.
  - Fragment of "Lecture on Defoe", [n.d]; TM (Box 1, Folder 31)
    2 leaves. In Italian, with carbon copy. The lecture was delivered in Trieste, in March 1912. The typescript itself dates from much later. Scholes 44.
  - Listing of his books [partial], [n.d.]; AM (Box 1, Folder 32)
    1 leaf. List in James Joyce's hand of 51 volumes on "Shelf 3: Front" and 32 volumes on "Shelf 3: Back." Scholes 1400.
  - "Il Miraggio del Pescatore di Aran", Sept. 2, 1912; TM (Box 1, Folder 33)
    6 leaves. Written in Galway. Text, in Italian, with English translation, of an article published by Joyce in the Sept. 5, 1912 edition of Il Piccolo della Sera. Scholes 39.
  - "New Tipperary" [carbon copies], ca. 1919; TM (Box 2, Folder 1)
    2 leaves. Written in Zurich. Doggerel verses on the Henry Carr incident. 2 carbon copies. Scholes 1410.
  - Notebook containing translation into Italian of Chapters 1 and 2 of George Moore's Celibates, [n.d.]; AM (Box 2, Folder 2)
    55 leaves. With corrections in another hand. Not in Scholes.
  - Notebook listing four dreams, with interpretations of three of them by Joyce., 1916; AM (Box 2, Folder 3)
    2 leaves. Four dreams, apparently dreamt by Nora Joyce. Joyce dates the first dream as in the tercentenary of Shakespeare's death [1916]. This autograph manuscript of James Joyce is in a copybook bound in half cloth tucked under flimsy blue cardboard. The dreams are numbered 1-4 in red-orange crayon. The fourth dream lacks interpretation. Scholes 52.
  - Notebook "Notes on Ireland", 1907-1912; AM (Box 2, Folder 4)
    2 leaves. Material for Piccolo della Sera articles or lecture, "L'Irlanda Isola dei Santi e dei Savi" delivered in Trieste in 1912. Scholes 43.
  - Notes for "Lecture on Blake", 1919; AM (Box 2, Folder 5)
    20 leaves. Written in Trieste. A fragment of a draft, possibly final, of James Joyce's lecture on Blake, delivered in Italian in Trieste. This autograph manuscript consists of 2 unbound booklets of wove paper, each booklet made up of 10 leaves, sewn with a single gray thread. A translation of this manuscript in included in Critical Writings. Scholes 46.
  - Notes on Vico, [n.d.]; TM (Box 2, Folder 6)
    3 leaves. One page is written in English, the other two are in Italian. Not in Scholes.
  - "L'Ombre de Parnell", May 16, 1912; TM (Box 2, Folder 7)
    12 leaves. Written in Trieste. Published in Il Piccolo della Sera. With 2 English translations. Scholes 39.
  - "Oscar Wilde: Il Poeta di Salome'", Mar. 24, 1909; TM (Box 2, Folder 8)
    6 leaves. Written in Trieste. Text, in Italian, with English translation, of an article published by Joyce in Il Piccolo della Sera. Scholes 39.
  - Eight poems which were included in Pomes Penyeach, ca. 1904-1916; TM (Box 2, Folder 9)
    29 leaves. Typescripts and carbon copies of the following 8 poems: "Cabra," an early version of "Tilly"; "Watching the Needleboats at San Sabba"; "A Flower Given to My Daughter"; "She Weeps over Rahoon"; "Tutto e sciolto," an early version; "Simples"; "Flood"; "Nightpiece." Scholes 54.
  - Fragment of A Portrait of the Artist, ca. Jan. 1904; AM (Box 2, Folder 10)
    2 leaves. This manuscript in the hand of Stanislaus Joyce includes the first part of the narrative. This copy is on 3 sides of 2 leaves of paper. The narrative is continued only into the second paragraph and then abandoned. Scholes 35.
  - A Portrait of the Artist, Jan. 7, 1904; TM (Box 2, Folder 11)
    8 leaves. A typescript of this first brief sketch of James Joyce's novel. January 7, 1904 is the date of the autograph manuscript from which this typescript was made, but the copy itself was made by or for Stanislaus Joyce ca. 1928. The main outlines of the later work--and even some of the incidents--are here in this sketch of January 1904. Scholes 34.
  - "The Right Heart in the Wrong Place", ca. Aug. 1920; AM (Box 2, Folder 12)
    1 leaf. Written in Paris, with envelope addressed to Stanislaus Joyce. Poem is written on one side of a plain card, signed "S.O.S." Scholes 59.
  - "The Right Man in the Wrong Place", ca. Aug. 1920; AM (Box 2, Folder 13)
    1 leaf. Written in Paris. Poem is written on one side of a plain card, signed "J.J." Scholes 59.
  - Latin poem- "Seduxit miles virtutem", [n.d.]; AM (Box 2, Folder 14)
    2 leaves. A Latin poem in James Joyce's hand on 2 paper slips of the size used by the National Library in Ireland. Scholes 1443.
  - Notebook labeled "Shakespeare", ca. 1912 [?]; AM (Box 2, Folder 15)
    5 leaves. Material for lecture delivered in 1912? A chronological listing of Shakespeare's activities to 1606. Not in Scholes.
  - Fragment of "Stephen Hero", ca. Jan. 1905; AM (Box 2, Folder 16)
    5 leaves. This autograph manuscript consists of 5 leaves of thin white wove paper, the versos blank except for the large page numbers: 479, 480, 490, 498, 506. These pages are missing from the Yale manuscript of a chapter of Stephen Hero (Slocum E3bii) and from the edition published by New Directions (New York, 1955). Scholes 36.
  - Telegraphic code prepared by Joyce, probably in connection with his Volta Theatre project, 1909 [?]; AM (Box 2, Folder 17)
    1 leaf. Autograph manuscript on one page of wove paper. "Codice" is written at the top of the page. On the left side of the recto is a list of code words in Italian. Opposite each of these words is a phrase or sentence for which the word is to stand. The code is continued on the upper half of the verso. Scholes 40.
  - Translation into Italian of a poem by James Stephens, "Stephen's Green" [copy], 1932 or earlier; TM (Box 2, Folder 18)
    1 leaf. Carbon copy of James Stephen's poem and an Italian translation of it by James Joyce. "James Stephens" typed at the end of the poem, "James Joyce" typed at the end of the translation. The title of the translation has been corrected in pencil by James Joyce to "Il Vento (nel parco di Stephen, Dublino)." Scholes 62.
  - "Trust Not Appearances", ca. 1893-98; AM (Box 2, Folder 19)
    1 leaf. Written in Belvedere College. One of the weekly compositions written by James Joyce for George Dempsey's class in English at Belvedere College. An autograph essay on the first 3 pages of a ruled double-leaf torn from the center of a copybook. At the top of each page is the motto "AMDG"; at the bottom of the last page ".LSD." Scholes 1.
  - Notes for "Cyclops" episode of Ulysses, [n.d.]; AM (Box 2, Folder 20)
    1 leaf. A list of characters for the "Cyclops" chapter. Autograph manuscript on the back of a letter from Henry Davray, dated June 23, 1919, on blue stationary of the Anglo-French Review. It is written in pencil, with the title "Cyclops" in a circle at the top of the page. Scholes 55.
  - Typescript of the "Nausicaa" episode of Ulysses [copy], Late 1919; TM (Box 2, Folder 21)
    21 leaves. Copy of typescript in box 2, folder 22. Scholes 57.
  - Typescript of the "Nausicaa" episode of Ulysses, Late 1919; TM (Box 2, Folder 22)
    21 leaves. A complete draft, close to the published version; with autograph corrections in the author's hand. There are some corrections and changes in ink in James Joyce's hand. The manuscript consists of 21 leaves numbered in pencil, 1-9, 9a, 10-20. Scholes 57.
  - Draft of the "Nausicaa" episode of Ulysses, Autumn 1919; AM (Box 2, Folder 23)
    16 leaves. A draft of the last half of the "Nausicaa" chapter. This autograph manuscript of James Joyce is contained in two identical notebooks with covers of thick purple paper. Both notebooks have blank labels pasted on their front covers. The labels are decorated with identical red borders except that the label of the first notebook has a red anchor and the letters "C G" worked into the lower margin. Scholes 56.
  - Fragment of "Oxen of the Sun" episode from Ulysses, [n.d]; AM (Box 2, Folder 24)
    5 leaves. This autograph manuscript of James Joyce contains a draft of the end of the "Oxen of the Sun" chapter with corrections in the left margins. Not in Scholes.
  - Two fragments of music- "Whittington Chimes" and "Ca ira", ca. 1916-1920; AM (Box 2, Folder 25)
    1 leaf. These two fragments of music are in James Joyce's hand on the recto of the first leaf and the verso of the second leaf of a double-leaf of paper ruled for musical composition. The paper bears a printed design of a lion on a branch holding a shield with two stars and the name "ZURICH" over the notation "SCHUTZMARKE No. 8." Scholes 61.
  - Embryological chart for "Oxen of the Sun" episode of Ulysses, 1920; AM (Map-case B-7)
    1 large leaf. Drawn on one side of a leaf of wove paper are nine numbered ovals of different sizes representing the monthly stages of gestation. The ovals are in red ink, beginning with the smallest almost at the lower edge of the page, each successive oval including its predecessors, the last almost reaching the top of the page. At the apices of seven of the ovals are notations about the related stage in fetal development, written in ink in James Joyce's hand. The apex of the sixth oval is distinguished by a star in red ink. In the upper left corner in a large parenthesis is the notation "Oxen of the Sun." Scholes 58.
    Also includes annotations and transcription.
  - Alphabetical Notebook, ca. 1904-ca. 1914; 4609 Bd Ms 1
    A series of notes kept by James Joyce on the following subjects: Byrne (John Francis), Cosgrave (Vincent), Clancy (George Stephen), Casey (Joseph), Calvacanti [sic] (Guido), Dedalus (Stephen), Devin, Esthetic, England, Gogarty (Oliver Saint John), Gordon (Michael), Giorgino, Henry (Father William), Healy (Michael), Ireland, Jesus, Ibsen (Henrik), Jesuits, Lust, Mother, McCluskey, Nora Pappie, Prezioso (Roberto), Poppie, Roucati (Venanzio), Rogers, (Marcellus), Skeffington (Francis Joseph Christopher), Sordina (Conte Francesco), Shelley (Percy Bysshe), Uncle William, and Walshe (Louis). These autograph notes are contained in a thick notebook, bound in half cloth over red-and-black mottled boards, with marbled edges. There are 300 ruled leaves in the book. The leaves are divided by 25 red tabs with white letters and have been cut so as to display the tabs, which are arranged in alphabetical order from top to bottom. Much of the material in this book was used verbatim by James Joyce in his published works, especially Ulysses and Portrait. Scholes 25.
  - Banking, 1906-1909; 4609 Bd Ms 2
    A notebook on banking kept by James Joyce. These autograph writings are in a notebook, bound in half cloth over red-brown-and-white boards, with marbled edges. On the recto of the first page after the unruled end paper is the title, "Banking." The book consists of 138 ruled leaves. The book begins with the history of banking and continues through such subsections as "Clerical Work" and "The Stock Exchange." Scholes 38.
  - My Crucible, Stanislaus Joyce's Diary, Sept. 26, 1903-Apr. 27, 1905; 4609 Bd Ms 3
    Also on microfilm. A journal kept by Stanislaus Joyce. In this journal, Stanislaus Joyce used for his own purposes paper which had been previously used - mainly by James Joyce - for other purposes. The manuscript consists of 202 leaves and contains in addition to this journal the other manuscripts and fragments described as Scholes 5 (Miscellaneous fragments), 6 (Fragment of an essay, on subjugation), 7 (The study of languages), 8 (Royal Hibernian Academy: "Ecce Homo"), 9 (The Apocalypse of Saint John), 10 (Drama and Life), 11 (Medical notes), 12 "I said I will go down to where"), 13 (From Chamber Music, two early drafts of the opening lines of poem XXXVI), 14 (Fragment of an essay, on the French attempt to build an empire in North Africa), 15 (Three epiphanies: a) "Her arm is laid for a moment on my knees." b) "Faintly, under the heavy summer night." c) "She comes at night when the city is still."). Scholes 4.
  - Exiles, Spring 1918; 4609 Bd Ms 4 +++ [?]